{"tossups": [{"question": "<em>The first of these organizations was likely formed to circumvent the Smith-Connally Act.</em> James Carey sometimes gives his name to \"hybrid\" types of these organizations. The 2010 <em>SpeechNow</em> decision allowed one type of these organizations to accept unlimited donations for \"independent expenditures;\" that type is the \"Super\" one. For 10 points, what organizations use members' contributions to campaign for or against a particular candidate or ballot measure?", "answer": "<b><u>PAC</u></b>s [or <b><u>political action committee</u></b>s]  {I}", "metadata": "DW"}, {"question": "<em>The Poinsettia flower is named for the first holder of this position, Joel Roberts Poinsett.</em> While serving in this position, Dwight Morrow used the tactic of \"ham-and-eggs diplomacy.\" Henry Lane Wilson was recalled from this position for assisting a coup known as the \"Ten Tragic Days,\" which brought Victoriano Huerta to power. For 10 points, name this American diplomatic office whose holder resides in Mexico City.", "answer": "United States <b><u>Ambassador</u></b> to <b><u>Mexico</u></b> [or <b><u>Minister</u></b> to <b><u>Mexico</u></b>; or <b><u>Envoy</u></b> to <b><u>Mexico</u></b>]  {I}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em>One type of this object contained two distinct features called the porpax and antilabe, which</em> <em>made it easier to carry.</em> Greek hoplites used a form of this object called the <em>aspis</em>, which contained a double grip system. Roman legions used a large type of this object called a <em>scuta.</em> The testudo formation made use of these objects. Along with spears, this object was used in a phalanx formation. For 10 points, name this defensive item used to block enemy attacks.", "answer": "<b><u>shield</u></b>s [or <b><u>aspis</u></b> before mention; or <b><u>scuta</u></b> before mention]  {I}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em>The only political party formed in this polity was the Concordia Association.</em> A border dispute between this polity and a western neighbor led to the Battle of Khalkhin-Gol. Unit 731 carried out inhumane experiments in this state. The Lytton Report investigated an incident that led to its creation. This state was established after the Mukden Incident, and installed Puyi as Emperor. For 10 points, name this puppet state set up after Japan's invasion of Manchuria.", "answer": "<b><u>Manchukuo</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>Manchuria</u></b>]  {I}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em>The organization founded by this man went after an Assistant U.S. Attorney in Operation Big</em> <em>Mouth</em>. This man gathered such ships as the <em>Diana</em> and the <em>Athena</em> as his \"Sea Org,\" a naval force whose members sign a \"billion year contract.\" This inventor of the \"E-meter\" to measure people's \"static fields\" and author of <em>Dianetics</em> founded a religion most visibly concentrated in Clearwater, Florida and Hollywood, California. For 10 points, name this founder of the Church of Scientology.", "answer": "Lafayette Ronald <b><u>Hubbard</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>This man lost control of Kandahar to Abbas II of Persia</em>. This man built the Red Fort in a city he named after himself and commissioned the Peacock Throne.Due to the intrigues of Nur Jahan, this man rebelled against his father Jahangir. He was overthrown after his preferred heir Dara Shikoh was defeated by Aurangzeb, who imprisoned him in the Agra Fort. For 10 points, which Mughal emperor and husband of Mumtaz Mahal built the Taj Mahal?", "answer": "Shahabuddin Muhammad <b><u>Shah Jahan</u></b> [or Prince <b><u>Khurram</u></b>]  {I}", "metadata": "TR"}, {"question": "<em>This political party won many seats through a \"big loaf, little loaf\" campaign in 1906</em>. A prime minister from this political party pushed for the passage of the 1909 People's Budget. Leaders of this party unsuccessfully pushed for Irish Home Rule. In the early twentieth century, its leaders included H.H. Asquith, while its leader in the late nineteenth century was William Gladstone. For 10 points, name this British political party that ideologically opposed the Conservatives.", "answer": "<b><u>Liberal</u></b> Party  {I}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em>This man's lawyers claimed some of his instability was due to participating in Henry Murray's</em> <em>CIA experiments at Harvard</em>. This man used the signature \"FC,\" which stood for \"Freedom Club.\" This person wrote <em>Industrial Society and Its Future</em>, a manifesto denouncing modern technology, which he wanted published in exchange for him desisting from his violent deeds.For 10 points, name this anarchist who sent out numerous homemade explosive devices from 1978 to 1995.", "answer": "The <b><u>Unabomber</u></b> [or Theodore \u201cTed\u201d <b><u>Kaczynski</u></b>] >MC> {I}", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<em>One of this man's achievements is disputed by partisans of his rival, Jean-Joseph-Henri</em> <em>Toussaint (<b>pr. too-SAHN</b>)</em>. When this man went on a holiday, assistant Charles Cumberland forgot to treat chickens. He controversially injected Joseph Meister, the victim of a dog bite. By boiling broth in swan-neck flasks, this man disproved the theory of spontaneous generation. For 10 points, name this French chemist who created the first vaccines for rabies and anthrax.", "answer": "Louis <b><u>Pasteur</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<em>During one of his presidential campaigns, this man criticized his party's description of him</em> <em>as a \"Grand Old Man.\"</em> This man was once visited by Victor Berger, who gave him a copy of <em>Das Kapital</em> to read. This man ran for president five times as the candidate for the Socialist Party, one time during which he was imprisoned under the Espionage Act of 1917. This man helped lead the American Railway Union into the Pullman Strike. For 10 points, name this American socialist.", "answer": "Eugene Victor <b><u>Debs</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em>The second part of the Treaty of Greenwich was a marriage proposal to this person.</em> This person\u2019s private secretary and possible lover, David Rizzio, was murdered by Lord Ruthven. This person was implicated for killing her husband, Lord Darnley, in the Casket Letters. The Babington plot sought to install this person on the English throne. For 10 points, name this person who was executed by her cousin, Queen Elizabeth I.", "answer": "<b><u>Mary</u> </b>Queen of <b><u>Scots</u></b> [or <b><u>Mary Stuart</u></b>; <b><u>Mary I</u></b> of <b><u>Scotland</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This man led a 1969 anti-immigration march joined by Ralph Abernathy and earlier fought to</em> <em>end the bracero program.</em> Coretta Scott King visited this man during his 24-day hunger strike in 1972, which inspired him to originate the phrase \"Si, se puede (<b>pr. SEE say PWAY-day</b>).\" After a strike of Filipino laborers in Delano, California, this man encouraged a nationwide boycott of grapes. For 10 points, name this Mexican-American activist who led the United Farm Workers union.", "answer": "Cesar Estrada <b><u>Chavez</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This state's Rosemeade township produced thousands of clay pheasants.</em> Nearly a third of this state's population is composed of Norwegian-Americans. This state is home to a National Park named after a man who once ranched here before become president, Teddy Roosevelt. Thanks to this state's low unemployment rate, it has recently had the highest rate of population growth of any U.S. state. For 10 points, name this state in the Great Plains whose recent oil boom has benefited cities like Fargo and Bismarck.", "answer": "<b><u>North Dakota</u> </b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This man served as a wagoner on both Edward Braddock\u2019s and John Forbes\u2019s expeditions to</em> <em>Fort Duquesne (<b>pr. doo-KAIN</b>).</em> This man lost his son Israel at the Battle of Blue Licks, and was later captured by Chief Blackfish. This man was employed by Richard Henderson\u2019s Transylvania Company during an expedition on which he founded a namesake \u201cborough\u201d in Kentucky. For 10 points, name this frontiersman who blazed the Wilderness Road through the Cumberland Gap.", "answer": "Daniel <b><u>Boone</u></b> [accept <b><u>Boonesborough</u></b> after \u201cborough\u201d]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>The protagonist of a novel written in this language is wheelchaired to a recruitment office</em> <em>during World War I.</em> In a novel written in this language, a man is expelled from the Communist Party for writing \"Optimism is the opium of the people!\". <em>The Good Soldier Svejk (<b>pr. SHVIKE</b>)</em> and <em>The Joke</em> are written in this language, which was used to describe Tereza's observations of Alexander Dubcek (<b>pr. DOOB-check</b>). For 10 points, name this language used by Milan Kundera, who studied in Prague.", "answer": "<b><u>Czech</u></b> [or <b><u>Cestina</u></b>]", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "<em>A ruler of this empire sought to marry Dakhamunzu, the widow of a pharaoh.</em> Few records survive from this empire's Middle Kingdom, which ruled after the reign of Telepinu. This empire reached its greatest extent under Suppiluliuma I. Following a battle that involved heavy use of chariots, this empire's ruler Muwatalli II signed the earliest-known peace treaty with Ramses II.  For 10 points, name this Anatolian empire that clashed with Egypt at the Battle of Kadesh.", "answer": "<b><u>Hittite</u></b> Empire", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>After its founding, this organization was joined by many volunteers at the Port Royal</em> <em>Experiment.</em> This organization established a Washington, D.C. university named for its leader, the \"Christian General.\" That leader of this organization, Oliver O. Howard, hoped to implement the promise of \"forty acres and a mule.\" For 10 points, name this Reconstruction-era organization that sought to aid former slaves.", "answer": "<b><u>Freedmen</u></b>'s <b><u>Bureau</u></b> [or <b><u>Bureau of Refugees, Freedmen, and Abandoned Lands</u></b>]  The Bureau was ended in 1872, a year before the Colfax Massacre was carried out against freedmen in what Southern state?  ANSWER: <b><u>Louisiana</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em>This character mistakes Apple Computers for a fruit company.</em> While being presented with the Medal of Honor, this man shows Lyndon Johnson his rear end. This resident of Greenbow, Alabama is related to and named after the first Grand Wizard of the KKK. This man went on a cross-country run that lasted over three years. For 10 points, name this character portrayed by Tom Hanks who remarks that life is \"like a box of chocolates.\"", "answer": "<b><u>Forrest</u><u>Gump</u></b> [accept either]", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "<em>In one campaign, this king ordered the destruction of the Irminsul and took control of</em> <em>Eresburg.</em> This ruler took his ream off the gold standard, setting up the livre. The baptism of Widukind ended his involvement in the Saxon Wars. This king included Alcuin (<b>pr. AL-koo-in</b>) of York and his biographer, Einhard, in his court. This son of Pepin the Short initially shared the throne with his brother Carloman I. For 10 points, name this great Frankish king.", "answer": "<b><u>Charlemagne</u></b> [or <b><u>Charles the Great</u></b>; or <b><u>Carolus Magnus</u></b>; or <b><u>Charles I</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This idea is the subject of</em> Patriarcha <em>by Robert Filmer.</em> This concept is supported in a manual addressed to Henry Frederick, the<em> Basilikon Doron</em>. Jacques-Benigne Bossuet argued for this idea. Romans 13 was often used to support this concept, which is similar to the Confucian Mandate of Heaven and was symbolized by the use of holy oil during coronations. For 10 points, name this doctrine which claims that monarchs derive authority from God.", "answer": "<b><u>divine right</u></b> of kings [prompt on answers like \"absolutism\" or \"monarchism\"]  What poet attacked the divine right concept in <em>The Tenure of Kings and Magistrates</em>, and also championed freedom of speech in <em>Areopagitica</em>?  ANSWER: John <b><u>Milton</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This man hypothesized the existence of an \u201caperiodic crystal\u201d that contains genetic</u></b></em> <em><b><u>information in his book What is Life?</u> </b></em><b><u>In the paper \u201cQuantization as an Eigenvalue</u></b> <b><u>Problem\u201d, this man presented a result often stated as the Hamiltonian of psi equals energy</u></b> <b><u>times psi. Eugene Wigner extended an idea named for this man by proposing Wigner's (+)</u>\u201cfriend\u201d; in this man's original setup, a radioactive source determines whether a (*) </b>hammer shatters a container of poison and kills an animal. For 10 points, name this Austrian physicist, the namesake of a thought experiment involving a simultaneously living and dead cat.", "answer": "Erwin <b><u>Schrodinger</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "EM"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This leader used the incomes of clergy to establish the Board of First Fruits and a</u></b></em> <em><b><u>namesake \"Bounty\" for poor clergy</u></b></em><b><u>. After Henry Sacheverell preached against</u></b> <b><u>nonconformists, this monarch's minister Sidney Godolphin had him tried for sedition.</u></b> <b><u>Abigail Masham replaced Sarah Churchill as this ruler's (+)</u>favorite. The war named for this monarch was the American theater of the War of Spanish Succession.(*)</b> This queen's eighteen pregnancies failed to produce an heir. For 10 points, name this English queen who succeeded William and Mary.", "answer": "Queen <b><u>Anne</u></b> I  {I}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This man was unsuccessfully sued by Charlotte Dupuy for her freedom.</u></b></em><b><u> During one</u></b> <b><u>campaign, this man issued the \"Alabama Letter\" detailing the conditions under which he</u></b> <b><u>would support Texas statehood. He and John (+)</u> Calhoun pushed through the Senate the 1833 Tariff Act that helpeddefuse the nullification crisis. This man sponsored the (*) </b>Maysville Road Bill that would have built a road in his home state of Kentucky as part of his \"American System.\" For 10 points, name this longtime leader of the Whig Party, known as the \"Great Compromiser.\"", "answer": "Henry <b><u>Clay</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "DW"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This person fled one event on a ship called the Vulture.</u></b></em><b><u> This husband of Peggy Shippen</u></b> <b><u>helped relieve the siege of Fort Stanwix. Along with Ethan Allen, this person helped (+)</u> capture Fort Ticonderoga, and he built a fleet to defend Lake Champlain, winning the Battle of Valcour Island. He was stripped of command despite defending Bemis (*)</b> Heights at the Battle of Saratoga. This person\u2019s plot was discovered after the capture of Major Andre. For 10 points, name this general who attempted to betray West Point to the British during the American Revolution.", "answer": "Benedict <b><u>Arnold</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "JZ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This man angrily responded to a remark given by the Filipino delegate Lorenzo Sumulong.</u> </b></em><b><u>This leader remarked that \"Whether you like it or not, history is on our side.\" A speech</u></b> <b><u>given by this man sparked the March 9 protests in (+)</u>Tbilisi, Georgia. This man, who emphasized the harmful consequences of a \"cult of personality,\" also told Western ambassadors \"We will (*)</b> bury you\" and may have banged his shoe at a United Nations meeting. For 10 points, name this Soviet leader whose \"Secret Speech\" denounced the rule of his predecessor, Joseph Stalin.", "answer": "Nikita Sergeyevich <b><u>Khrushchev</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<b><u>In the early 2000\u2019s, this musician was frustrated by university officials in his attempts to</u></b> <b><u>take classes at Princeton. This musician covered folk songs popularized by the title man in</u></b> <em><b><u>We Shall Overcome: The Seeger Sessions.</u> </b></em><b><u>He was inspired by the NYPD shooting of</u></b> <b><u>Amadou Diallo to write \u201cAmerican (+)</u>Skin (41 Shots).\u201d He included a tribute song, \u201cMy City Of Ruins,\u201d on his 2002 album </b><em><b>The Rising</b></em><b>. His song about a bitter Vietnam veteran \u201cborn (*)</b> down in a dead man\u2019s town\u201d was briefly used in Ronald Reagan\u2019s 1984 re-election campaign. For 10 points, name this New Jersey songwriter who performed \u201cBorn In The U.S.A.\u201d with his E Street Band.", "answer": "Bruce <b><u>Springsteen</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "CW"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This event was ended when John Litster was defeated by the Bishop of Norwich.</u> </b></em><b><u>Many</u></b> <b><u>participants in this human-driven event were angered by the Statute of Labourers.</u></b> <b><u>Participants in this event captured the Savoy Palace. Robert (+)</u>Hales and Simon of Sudbury were killed during this event. After a meeting at Mile End, the leader of this rebellion went to (*)</b> Smithfield and was killed by William Walworth. Richard II put down this rebellion, which was sparked by an unpopular poll tax. For 10 points, name this 1381 uprising led by Wat Tyler.", "answer": "English <b><u>Peasant</u></b>s\u2019 <b><u>Revolt</u></b> of 1381 [or <b><u>Wat Tyler\u2019s Revolt</u></b> before \u201cWat\u201d is read]  {I}", "metadata": "SH"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Aleixo Garcia and Sebastian Cabot went on journeys to find a legendary mountain where</u></b></em> <em><b><u>this resource could be found.</u> </b></em><b><u>This resource is the most significant part of the economy in</u></b> <b><u>Chanarcillo. The Chichimeca War was fought on paths named after (+)</u>this resource that originated in Zacatecas, Mexico. Mitayos were people who mined this resource through working in the (*)</b> Mit'a system. In the New World, this resource was mined in locations such as the Cerro Rico in Potosi. For 10 points, name this precious metal often used in currency.", "answer": "<b><u>silver</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>During the 1970's, this city was home to the \"Hole in the Wall\" gang.</u> </b></em><b><u>A newspaper in this</u></b> <b><u>city printed the \"Where I Stand\" article accusing Joseph McCarthy of homosexuality. Pat</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u>McCarran lobbied for the construction of Nellis Air Force Base outside this city. After failing to make the Flamingo Hotel in this city profitable, Bugsy (*)</b> Siegel was murdered. Boulder City was created to keep construction workers on the Hoover Dam out of this city. For 10 points, name this city that adopted a slogan saying what happens in this city stays in this city.", "answer": "<b><u>Las Vegas</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "DW"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>The artist of a painting depicting this war described the central figure as \"a vast human</u></b></em> <em><b><u>body breaking out into monstrous excrescences of arms and legs tearing at one another.\"</u> </b></em><b><u>This</u></b> <b><u>war inspired the painting</u> </b><em><b><u>Soft Construction</u></b><b><u>with Boiled Beans</u></b></em><b>. (+) Another painting about this war shows a hand grasping a broken sword at its bottom, while above it a (*)</b> horse rears its head to the left of a woman holding a candle. That painting shows the bombing of a Basque town during this war. For 10 points, name this war depicted in Pablo Picasso's <em>Guernica</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Spanish Civil War</u></b>  {I}  <b>Extra Tossup </b> This is a tossup provided for breaking ties or replacing a flubbed or erroneous question at any point in the packet. The power marks are provided so that it may be scored according to fourth quarter rules if it is replacing a fourth quarter question. The power marks should be ignored if this tossup is used to replace a first or second quarter question.", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>A controversial 1872 election for this position led to a split between the \"Minstrels\" and</u></b></em> <em><b><u>\"Brindle Tails.\"</u></b></em><b><u> One person who held this position commuted the death sentences of fifteen</u></b> <b><u>inmates after losing a re-election campaign to Dale (+)</u>Bumpers. Another holder of this position deployed the National Guard to prevent nine students from (*)</b> attending Central High School. Winthrop Rockefeller and Orval Faubus held, for 10 points, what position also held by Bill Clinton when he ran for President in 1992?", "answer": "<b><u>governor</u></b> of <b><u>Arkansas</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>governor</u></b>]  {I}", "metadata": "DW"}], "bonuses": []}